Okay בוקר
טוב *Boker Tov*.
We are in חודש טוב *Chodesh Tov*.
That's correct.
Today's דף daf. ס"ו *Daf Samech Vav*, we're going to pick up
on the עמוד ב' *Amud Bet* right before
the, actually I don't know how many lines it is, but it's
by the first two dots
somewhat in the middle-ish of the page. משכנו לו בית *Mishkeno lo
bayit*.
It had five lines underneath the תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* where it says
לא *Lo*.
Yeah, correct. That's where we are. Okay fine. So how to vocalize
this is they punctuate this as משכן *Mishken*. It's from the word
משכון mashkon, *Mashkon*. So you collateralized. That's basically what that means. So
not משכן *Mishkan*. משכון mashkon,
*Mashkon* would be the collateral, משכן *Mishken* is the act of doing
it, so it's בניין פיעל *Binyan Pi'el*. So anyway, so okay, so
משכנו לו בית *Mishkeno lo bayit*. So if there's a loan, we're
continuing with this משנה mishna. *Mishna*. By the way,
a major focus of today is going to be the idea of
אסמכתא asmachta, *Asmachta*, which we'll define. And also just remember the end
of the משנה mishnah *Mishna* was that if you, this practice that
בייתוס בן זונין *Baitus ben Zonin* used to do, that he basically
used to take a field that was worth far more than the
loan and once the loan horizon was met and if it wasn't
repaid, he took the collateral field. Right? So we'll have to figure
out about all these different things, differences between a sale versus a
loan in land versus מטלטלין metaltelin. *Metaltelin*. We're going to discuss all
these things.
And how clear is the משכון mashkon *Mashkon*? Yes, so that was
למשכן את הבית *Le-mishken et ha-bayit*.
Exactly. Or שדה *Sadeh* or a בית *Bayit*. ולא תהא נקנית לו
אלא בדמים הללו bedamim halalu, *Ve-lo tehe niknit lo ela bidamim hallalu*.
So he said, okay,
he
sort of locks him in. So he said, the, in
this
case, sometimes there's a buyer and there's a seller, but here there's
the lender and then there's the borrower. So the lender, so remember,
this is worth more than the amount of the loan, right? So
he said, okay, listen, I know
you may not be able to repay this loan too well, right?
I know you're going to have problems and guess what, I have
this field, right? So sell it to just me, לא תיקנה אלא
לי בדמים הללו *Lo tikaneh ela li bidamim hallalu*. I'm the only
one that can get it and they fixed the price. Right? But
okay, well, what's the problem with that? The problem is, it isn't
mentioned in the גמרא gemara *Gemara*, but the price that you fixed
for that is less than the loan. Right? So basically what essentially,
in some ways this is almost like interest, right? Because you know
for the fact that I'm not getting any interest on this loan,
I'm going to be able to use this field to collect
at a lesser price than it's worth, which means I'm basically gaining
the difference.
I have a question.
You get what I'm saying? Right? Before you have the question. Right?
So like he's coming out ahead by getting a field that's worth
more for less than it's worth. Right? Which is almost sort of
like
interest. Right? Okay. But if you said and you actually, so you
fix the price like now. אסור asur
*Asur* בשוויין *Be-shaveiyen*, but if you did it for whatever the market
value of this field is, then מותר mutar. *Mutar*. So, and remember
he tells him, he's going to sell him this field but why
would he sell him the field, why didn't he just collect it
as part of the collateral? Because again, it's worth more,
right? So and it's only, and it's okay, I'll quote unquote sell
you this field and okay, we'll repay the loan with it. You
know what I mean? So it's sort of like a,
it is a משכון mashkon *Mashkon*, but since the loan is worth
a hundred and the field is worth a hundred and fifty, right?
So if he said
that I'm going to do it for less than, I'm going to
do it for a hundred and twenty-five, right? And then he's going
to, so he's going to pay him I guess the extra twenty-five.
You know what I mean? Because a hundred dollars will go towards
the payment of the loan and then twenty-five dollars will go
towards the extra value of the field. But really this borrower loses
out on twenty-five because it's really worth a hundred and fifty. So
essentially, like this guy is getting interest, right? Because that, okay. But
if he said, okay, it's worth a hundred and fifty, you sell
it to me for a hundred and fifty, you take a hundred
in payment of your loan, I get the fifty more that it's
worth and the field really is worth a hundred and fifty, then
that's just, it's not a hundred percent arms-length transaction, but enough for
these purposes. But again, like the key line is that
you're selling
it.
So what is the difference between this case and buying a house
and taking a mortgage?
In other words, it's a loan, I can't pay the loan back
so the bank repossesses my house. I remember mortgage is משכנתא.
Right, 100%.
So is this basically saying that that type of transaction where you
take out a loan in order to buy a house, you don't
pay the loan back, so then the guy gets the house, the
guy is the bank, but some guy it's the same case?
But it would sell the house and has to give you back
any excess that it makes beyond what it takes to pay off
the loan.
Right, that's today in secular law. Right.
I didn't realize that. Yeah. So if you owe $100,000 on a
house and you get foreclosed on and they sell it at auction
for $200,000, you get a check from the bank for $100,000 less
the cost of the auctioneer and stuff.
But if it's worth less and the bank holds on to it,
which would be then this whole case of
and you still have an unsecured let's say they sell for $50,000,
you still have a loan for $50,000 with the bank plus the
cost of the auctioneer, and it becomes an unsecured loan where they
will demand that money.
Right, so this isn't exactly like צד אחד בריבית,
tzad
echad beribit, right? Because, you know, like yeah,
so which itself is a מחלוקת. machloket. Okay, so
we just said בדמים הללו, you know, you made a specified fixed
and reduced price. So who is that? מאן תנא בדמים הללו אסור?
man tana bedamim halalu assur? So who is
this that taught this? אמר רב הונא בר יהודה רב יהושע דלא
כרבי יהודה, Amar Rav Huna bar Yehuda Rav Yehoshua de'lo ke'Rabbi Yehuda,
דאי כרבי יהודה האמר צד אחד בריבית מותר.
de'ee ke'Rabbi Yehuda ha'amar tzad
echad beribit mutar.
So
this is not like Rabbi Yehuda because Rabbi Yehuda again we have
this whole מחלוקת machloket as to if it's not certain that it'll
end up in ריבית, ribit, that's צד אחד בריבית. tzad echad beribit.
Right, like, you know, like let's say it could depreciate. Exactly. No,
I know, I know. So Rabbi Yehuda said as long as it's
not a fait accompli that this will turn into ריבית, ribit, then
that would be okay. So here
too, is this צד אחד בריבית? tzad echad beribit? Why? Because he
says, and this is like the key phrase over here,
לכשתרצה, likshe'tirtze, right? If you're going to sell it. Let's say he
decides not to sell it. He decides, you know, I'll pay it
back. I don't No, that's fine. I have the money. You know,
time for the loan comes due, I pay the money, that's it,
right? So then he pays him his hundred dollars. You know, so
even if they contracted for a reduced price, right? The field's worth
150, sold for 125, but he didn't have to, he could have
always paid him back the value of the loan and then get
his field back. So since it's not inevitable that this would have
resulted in, you know,
we'll say, אונאה ona'ah to the borrower, then he would have said
that it's okay. So however, the teaching was that it's not okay,
so it's not like Rabbi Yehuda. Okay? So next. מה זה ma
ze צד אחד בריבית? tzad echad beribit?
What is that definition again, צד אחד בריבית? tzad echad beribit?
Like meaning that it's, the way I mean, literally it means one-sided
ריבית. ribit. Like, you know, like meaning one side, one way it
can turn out to be ריבית ribit if things work out, you
know, according to that way. If it really works out that he
ends up not having enough money and wants to sell this field
to him, it results in ריבית. ribit. Okay, then, you know, then
that's the way, that's one possibility. But there's another possibility, there's a
צד אחר tzad acher for the transaction, for the events to unfold.
And if the events unfold differently, it won't result, you know, in
ריבית. ribit. In other words, you could decide not to sell. You
know, in other words, if I, if we you and I have
a loan, which doesn't make a difference which one of us is
who, and we say, all right, well I'm going to borrow five
and pay you back six, there's no way around it, right? That's
ריבית. ribit. It will inevitably result in ריבית. ribit. But over here,
you may not want to sell the field and you end up
repaying the loan.
So but he can still buy it at the reduced price? No!
If he according oh right, no, right, he could, it would be
permitted to buy it at a reduced price because it is his
option to sell it to him at a reduced price. It's not
inevitable he'll end up selling it because he could just repay the
loan. Okay.
So that means that in that situation there was no initial arrangement
that he would sell it at the reduced price?
There was no initial obligation. There was initial arrangement that if he
were to sell it, he would sell it at the reduced price.
Oh, I see. Okay.
But then it says above for the first case it says according
to this translation, well if you ever decide to sell it. If
you ever decide, if you
decide you want to sell. So that's why Rabbi Yehuda is saying
it's okay?
Yeah, that's right.
Because you could decide not to sell. Okay. Right. Yeah. Okay. But
it is not, but that's what it says for the, for the
first case, it says, according to this translation, well, or if you
ever decide to sell it. If you ever decide, if you, if
you decide you want to sell it. Oh, so that's why רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is saying it's okay. Yeah, right, because he could
decide not to sell it.
Oh, okay. Right. Okay.
מכר לו בית machar lo bayit
מכר לו שדה machar lo sadeh אמר לו amar lo כשיהיו לך
מעות kesheyihyu lecha maot החזירם לי hahzirem li אסור asur, וכשיהיו לך
מעות u-chesheyihyu lecha maot אחזירם לך achazirem lecha מותר. mutar.
So basically what I have over here, since this is not a
משכון, mashkon, this is a different case. So let's just
leave that aside and we're going to get into these
things, similar concept, you'll see. So
again on the board. So this כשיהיו לי מעות החזירם לי. kesheyihyu
li maot hahzirem li.
So the seller just says to the buyer, okay listen, I'm kind
of stuck right now, so I'm going to sell this field to
you because I need the money, you know, whatever it is, and
I'll sell it. I'm just saying that as background but like you
just sort of understand the concept. So then the seller, the מוכר
mocher says to the לוקח, lokeach, when I get money, you know,
just return it to me. I sold you for a hundred dollars,
I don't have it right now, maybe in a year from now,
whatever it is, I'm going to have the money and then you
sell it back to me. All right. So then אסור, asur,
but the other way around and we'll discuss why. You know, the
other way around is let's say the buyer says to the seller,
okay look, I know you really didn't want to sell this, but
you know, I'll tell you what, look I want it now, I'll
do whatever it is I need to use it for whatever it
is I need to. But I'll make you the deal, כשיהיו לך
מעות אחזירם לך, kesheyihyu lecha maot achazirem lecha, when you have enough
money to buy it back from me, I'll sell it to you,
I won't sell it to anyone else. Okay, that's okay. So
let's
discuss that, so we're going to
try to understand that. Yeah.
I'm sorry, can you just repeat what the cases are here, the
two ones here?
מכר לו בית machar lo bayit מכר לו שדה. machar lo sadeh.
So someone, there's a buyer and there's a seller and the transaction
was for a house or for a field, it doesn't matter what
it was for. So then
ואמר לו, ve-amar lo, so the question is who said to whom?
So ואמר לו ve-amar lo is the מוכר mocher said to the
לוקח. lokeach. So the seller says to the buyer, כשיהיו לי, kesheyihyu
li, I'm sorry, כשיהיו לי מעות החזירם לי. kesheyihyu li maot hahzirem
li. So when you come up with the money, when I come
up with the money, right, bring it back, give it back to
me. So
the מוכר mocher says to the לוקח, lokeach, you know, כשיהיו לי
מעות החזירם לי. kesheyihyu li maot hahzirem li. So you sold him
this
house and now he's saying when I have money, I'll buy it
back.
I'll buy it back to you, I'll buy it back from you.
I didn't really want to do this essentially. Exactly, he sold my
house.
No, it's a loan, that's the problem.
He's
defining
it as a loan which is the problem.
So but the other way around, if he voluntarily, if the buyer
voluntarily says to the
seller, all right listen, if you want to, when you come up
with the money at some point, I'll give it back to you.
I mean you'll pay me for it obviously, but so that's okay.
So anyway now we're going to discuss this. So the first case,
why is it a problem? Well, think about it,
this could be a year later, that's why I said that example.
Right? So he'll give it back to him, the seller, so what
happens? So a hundred dollars goes one way, a hundred dollars goes
back the other way, and meanwhile
this guy's had it the whole time, he had the פירות, peirot,
which is sort of the problem
of our משנה. Mishnah? That's why it's אסור, asur. right?
Let me put it in a little bit more here. That's why
it's אסור. asur.
So but doesn't the תורה Torah have an example of what to
do with the כהנים kohanim where they can sell, they always have
the right of redemption?
Well that's
to with הקדש hekdesh or something that כהנים kohanim use it, but
that's in the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. Not in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, I mean in
the original entering the land
and there's a difference between a house in a walled city and
a house outside of a walled city, there's certain
examples where
you can redeem the house.
One second.
Awkward silence, but I'm just writing on the board.
Okay here, so this is, that's the problem of being a lefty.
Your hand goes over everything you write when you write in English.
Just write from right to left.
That's what Leonardo da Vinci did.
He was a lefty
so he
wrote in Italian from right to left.
And in reverse also.
He was a lefty so he wrote, yeah. So okay, anyway, so
here just so we're clear because it gets a little confusing, so
what is it, essentially a repurchase, the first case where it's אסור.
Assur. So meanwhile Meanwhile the buyer gets exactly what he paid for,
he gets his money back, right, in that event. But meanwhile the
buyer has it in his possession the entire time. So that's like
ריבית. Ribbis. If he has investment in his entire time, I mean
if it was just like a fallow field, I guess, you know,
maybe less of a problem, but you know, you get to eat
the...
although I don't know, I'm not going to say that.
The possession the whole time.
The buyer, the buyer you know, so the seller says you know
I'm going to, you know, I'm selling it to you now, right,
and when- but I'm going to repurchase it from you. Right. So
meanwhile, me and you, right, I buy back from you. Meanwhile, you
have my fields for a year, and you're using it.
But it's mine.
I understand, but I'm going to buy back from you.
Okay, it's two separate things.
But then it looks like...
I hear you. You sell me the property, now it's mine. I'm
eating the apples all year. Then you say, I have money now,
will you sell it back to me, and I say yes. What's
the
problem?
Because you're contracting this from the very beginning, right? It seems like
almost this is a stipulation of the sale.
But then,
then the sale's more like a sham, it's more like a loan.
Why? That's what I don't get. Why is this sale like a
loan?
Cause he did it from the very...
that I mean I think because you know because this happens from
the very beginning.
They've agreed to reverse the
transaction. Right. Got you.
I get it.
But the other case,
it's so interesting because it's all a verbal structuring. Yeah. In other
words if you didn't verbally structure it that way, it's a real
sale.
Right, like the second case.
Maybe
I'll buy it back, and maybe I won't.
I get it. That's so interest- it's like hard to wrap my
mind around. Yeah, it's like I really own the field now, it's
really mine, but we structured it such that I've got an obligation
to sell it back to
you.
Right.
Right, so I will have taken פירות peiros literally, I've been eating
those apples. Yeah, but it's really the same as... it really is
mine, I can do anything I want during that time.
There's also a note here that says if the seller dies, then
retroactively it is a
sale. There's a note from...
yeah, because
I guess then
his death forgives the
loan.
There's a note by... there's a note in Steinsaltz, the רמב"ן Ramban
says that this transaction actually doesn't go through. Really? What does he
say?
The רמב"ן. Ramban. Well we said it's אסור. Assur. We said it's
אסור. Assur. Okay, but anyway, but the other way around is the
buyer voluntarily, you know, let- yeah, the buyer- the buyer voluntarily made-
I just want to move on cause you know we're not even
on today's דף. daf, That you know the- the buyer- the buyer
says to the seller, לך שיהיו לך מעות אחזירן לך, lech she-yeheyu
lecha maos achzirein lach, so in that kind of a case, that
is okay. Now we're going to, now we're going to, you know,
figure this out a little bit. מאן תנא? Man tana?
Who's this? אמר רבה בר רב הונא, Amar Rabbah bar Rav Huna,
לא כרבי יהודה. lo ke-Rabbi Yehuda. דאי כרבי יהודה, De-ee ke-Rabbi Yehuda,
sounds familiar, דאי כרבי יהודה, de-ee ke-Rabbi Yehuda, הצד אחד בריבית מותר.
hama'amad tzad echad beribbis mutar. So he would say that it would
be okay. So, in other words, again, who's to say they're ever
going to get the money? Right? If I have money, right? So
we said it was אסור. So, but
again,
like it's if you will have money, then it'll be a problem.
But see, you never have money.
You never have money, so I have the field and it's you
know, I'm not eating any interest. You never- you never buy back,
right? So it's not inevitable that- that this will result
in- in quote-unquote interest. I'm calling it interest because that's what the
problem is. So it's not like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay, but...
okay, so now we're going to try to figure out here and
here, right? Why is this not okay, but the second part is,
when the buyer voluntarily says it? מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא?
Mai shna reisha u-mai shna seifa? That's that- that's what that means,
you know, the רישא reisha of what we just taught over here.
So, אמר רבא, amar Rava, so here's a little- it's- so a
little bit of a, you know, question of what the גרסא girsa
is. I'll read it this way. רישא דלא אמר לדעתיה אבל סיפא
דאמר ליה לדעתיה. Reisha delo amar lada'atei, aval seifa de-amar lei lada'atei.
So it doesn't see- so this is the thing, like, in other
words, if you're locked into it, right, then אין הכי נמי, ein
hachi nami, then that'd be a problem also, right? But לך שיהיו
לך מעות אחזירן לך lech she-yeheyu lecha maos achzirein lach is not,
we're saying, an iron-clad condition of a contract that you must- it's
like, if I you know, if you want to, you know, let's-
you know
we'll do it, but like I'll consider it, meaning. That's what it
means. It means like maybe, you know, like... and you know טאקע
taka but that might be a good idea, but I'm not- basically
saying, you know, he's basically saying that to make him feel better
really. Like, you know, but wait- but wait- but he's not like,
you know, at least the way I understood it, I think there's
a תוספות tosafot here, or maybe it's רש"י. Rashi.
The assumption here is that the repurchase would be at the same
price, so that...
oh, that's interesting.
Meaning the buyer isn't assuming any kind of risk of gain or
loss in terms of
market fluctuation.
It would have to be at the value at the time, right?
Not the price that you sold it for.
Because if it's the value at the time then it seems hard
to see why...
No, no, it's for it to be for it to be okay,
meaning, you know, like I'll repurchase it from you for the, you
know, whatever value it is then.
Because it's more of a loan if it's back at the original.
Well, well, it's more like a loan, in which case it would
be let's
let's think about this for a minute. If you're purchasing it back
from the price at, you know, at time A, the same price,
then,
you know, it could go up or down in value. Well, this
certainly already is not like Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So
let's say even according to the Hakhamim
חכמים, Hakhamim, I don't
know,
it would seem to me that then, you know, that it'd be
even more of a problem if it was for the original, right?
If it was for the original, original value then it's really like
a loan.
Whereas
if the buyer has the benefit of, you know, if the price
goes up, then it looks more like a real sale with...
Right, that's what I'm saying. I mean, I'm agreeing that like it
would be if it's for the original price then that's even more
of a problem. Yeah. Yeah, but you know, but the question is,
you know, if you're still pledging to do it, am I still
quote-unquote ribbit ריבית, ribbit, because, you know, they don't care about avak
ribbit אבק ריבית, avak ribbit, they care about the fact that, you
know, that meanwhile you've in the interim, you know, so I think
it's a problem either way regardless of what you said. Because, you
know, if you because meanwhile it could potentially not increase or change
in value at all, in which case then it's been a loan
the entire time and you've managed to eat the peirot פירות. peirot.
So I I would say, although again this is just me sort
of thinking, you know, standing up here, not having considered this or
looked into anything, you know, that regardless it would be a problem.
That makes sense? So... Okay wait wait, let me just yeah, let
me just explain this case.
Yeah, it's on this exact case.
Likhsheyihyu lekha ma'ot akhzirem lakh לכשיהיו לך מעות אחזירם לך. Likhsheyihyu lekha
ma'ot akhzirem lakh. Yeah, no, no, I want to I didn't finish.
I just want to like let me see if I can explain
this. So what we're basically saying is that likhsheyihyu lekha ma'ot לכשיהיו
לך מעות, likhsheyihyu lekha ma'ot, just insert the word where he said,
kesheertzeh כשארצה. kesheertzeh. Basically, de'atei דעתי de'atei means kesheertzeh כשארצה. kesheertzeh. You
have to fill that in. Kesheertzeh כשארצה. kesheertzeh. Likhsheyihyu lekha ma'ot kesheertzeh
לכשיהיו לך מעות כשארצה. likhsheyihyu lekha ma'ot kesheertzeh. If I want to.
Akhzirem אחזירם, akhzirem, you have to say akhzirem אחזירם akhzirem implies ratzon
רצון. ratzon. Whereas hakhziram li החזירם לי hakhziram li in the reisha
רישא reisha is a stipulation in which there isn't any...
Exactly,
right.
Right, like hakhziram החזירם hakhziram is a stipulation at the beginning. Akhzirem
אחזירם, akhzirem, the pshat פשט pshat here seems to be in the
Talmud תלמוד Talmud that it implies I will return them to
you quote-unquote if I want to at the time.
Exactly, right. So basically, so what we're basically saying is this is
okay, and so because this sort of like answers your question, right?
Why isn't it considered a sale? Because, well, the answer is it
is considered a sale, exactly that. Because this is at time A,
right? And then time A has nothing to do with time B,
because time B may not, you know,
if he wants to sell it back, he does, if he doesn't
want to, he won't, right? It's not like A and B are
linked. You know what I mean?
So it's not like the
the the mortgage question also.
Yeah, no, I wanted to I wanted to get to that.
It's not like a mortgage.
I do want to get to that. I mean, I know that
it came up at some points here.
It's essentially the same,
so let's see how we we do over here. All right. So
now a couple of stories. De-hu gavra de-zaban ley ara lekhavrei דההוא
גברא דזבן ליה ארעא לחבריה de-hu gavra de-zaban ley ara lekhavrei shelo
ba'akhrayut שלא באחריות. shelo ba'akhrayut. So now usually... let me just translate
and then I'll say. So somebody sold land to somebody else and
you know the concept of akhrayut אחריות. akhrayut. Akhrayut אחריות akhrayut is
basically like a backstop, right? I'm good if anything goes wrong.
That's what
akhrayut אחריות akhrayut
is, right? It's an insurance? Essentially, yeah.
So now, you know, one thing to remember though, what usually happens
is,
do you know which if you don't, I'll tell you because, you
know, that
are
certain
things usually assumed to have this akhrayut אחריות? akhrayut?
Karka קרקע? karka? Exactly. So karka קרקע karka is usually devarim de-it
lehu akhrayut דברים דאית להו אחריות.
devarim de-it lehu akhrayut. Correct. So over here so this is a
very unusual case, right? Karka קרקע karka is generally assumed to have
akhrayut אחריות, akhrayut, and so much so if you also remember there
was a whole, you may or may not remember, like, you know,
that there is a makhloqet מחלוקת makhloqet as to let's say what
was left out and it's karka קרקע, karka, do you say akhrayut
ta'ut sofer אחריות טעות סופר? akhrayut ta'ut sofer? Remember that? Like if
the scribe just made a mistake. I mean, come on, like, you
know, you always add that in there. Right?
So
anyway,
so here, you know, so if we say that, then how does
this whole case get off the
ground, right? Very good. So,
that's how the whole case get off the ground. So you have
to say that it's actually stipulated in the contract that there will
be no אחריות, achrayut, right? So because otherwise how's this happen, we
say אחריות טעות סופר
הוא.
achrayut taut
sofer hu. Okay.
So רש''י Rashi says this: שאם יטרפנה בעל חוב she'im yetzorfennah ba'al
chov third line, now second line from the bottom, בעל חוב לי
לא אשלם לך כלום, ba'al chov li lo ashlem lecha klum, כגון
שפירש לו הכי בהדיא בשטר, kegon sheperash lo hachi behedya bashtar, ואם
מסתמא אוקמינן כשמואל דאמר אחריות טעות סופר. ve'im mistama amkinan keshmue'el de'amar
achrayut taut sofer. So basically he says, you know, it has to
be that this was stipulated in the contract that I'm not selling
to you with any guarantee, because we פסקן pasken already when we
have this debate as to if there's no guarantee by land, which
normally does have a guarantee, is that considered such a glaring omission
that it's as if it was in the contract? So we פסקן
pasken that that's what it is. So then in order for this
to even be a legitimate sale, it had to have been stipulated
in the contract that I'm not going to make good for you.
Anyway, so what happened? So חזייה
דהוה קא
עציב. chazayeh dehavah ka atziv. So this guy then realizes, the guy
who bought it, right, you know, realizes, like, what did I get
myself into? Right? This is קרקע. karka. Like, you know, if something
goes wrong, I'm stuck. So, you know, so then the seller saw
this buyer that he was kind of like sad about this, he
was upset about it, grumbling, right?
So אמר ליה אמאי צבית אי טרפו לה מינך מגבינא לך שופרא.
amar lei amai tzavit iy tarfu lah minach magvinah lakh shefra. You
know, you know, he said, I'll make good. Right? Once it was
stipulated in the contract that I'm not going to make good, then
he found him later and says, don't worry, I'll take care of
you. Right? I'll give you the best. Right? I'll give you good
stuff, don't worry.
Right? שופרא ושבחא ופירי. shefra ve'shevacha u'perei. I'll make you a hundred
percent good. You know, if they take, you know, if someone, if
my בעל חוב ba'al chov comes and you want, and you would
lose all these פירי perei you would have had, I'll make up
the value of the פירי, perei, if you put in money into
the property, I'll make up the, you know, I'll make that up
too. You know, you're not going to lose out at all.
This sounds like אחריות. achrayut. I'm sorry? This sounds like אחריות. achrayut.
Yeah, exactly.
Right, but he's doing it later, right? So that's the difference. אמר
אמימר, amar Ameimar, now רש''י Rashi on today's דף, פטומי מילי בעלמא
הוא. pitumei milah be'alma hu. Right? פטומי pitumei is a very interesting
word. Like, you know, if Rabbi Larry, you'll pick up on this,
what does פטומי pitumei mean?
פיטום הקטורת? pitum haketoret?
Well, פטומי pitumei means to fatten up. Exactly. Fatten like a goose.
Right, you fatten up an ox, like, you know, like so you're
fattening this guy, you're buttering him up essentially, right? You're like, yeah,
you're just saying that to, like, you know, you're filling him with
empty words, basically. That's what it's,
that's what, that's the import of this. Look at the רש''י: Rashi:
אין אלו
אלא דברי תנחומים בעלמא לפייסו. ein elu ela divrei tanchumim be'alma lifayeso.
They're just like, you know, like nice things to comfort him, but
you know, doesn't change the fact that you agreed in the contract
to not do it. You're making him feel good. So that's, so
what does it sound like? Remember what I start today by saying?
This sounds like almost like an אסמכתא, asmachta right? That's what, which
we'll describe more, but אסמכתא asmakhta is like, you know, a verbal
declaration, right? So like, you know, are verbal declarations binding? You said
this isn't in the contract, right? You said this to him afterwards.
So does this have a legally binding effect? That's the concept we're
going to start to introduce here. אמר ליה רב אשי לאמימר טעמא
מאי? amar lei Rav Ashi le'Ameimar taama mai? So okay, so אמימר
Ameimar said it's no good, right? Doesn't make a difference, right? You're
just talk, but you're not bound to this. That's what it means,
פטומי מילי בעלמא הוא, pitumei milah be'alma hu, just,
you know, fluff. So okay, so let's think about this, he's saying.
So why are you saying that it's not good? That's what he
means by this טעמא מאי. taama mai. משום דלוקח בעי לאתנויי. mishum
de'loke'ach ba'ei le'atnuyei. Usually
he, but you know, that if I'm buying something from you, right,
I'm going to try to make the stipulations in the contract. You
know, you enter a real estate, you know, we do this whole
time, in real estate, like you make all these, you know, the
condition of this land will be purchased following conditions, right? There's no
problem with the title, you know, we can develop it into whatever,
into this, no zoning regulatory restrictions, whatever it is. Right? You know,
I'm spending all this money, I want to make sure, you know,
I'm covered, right?
So פטומי מילי בעלמא הוא
pitumei milah
be'alma
hu means this is just verbal
stuff that's not binding. Exactly. There's no legal force.
Correct. Correct. So then the question is, you know, so he's saying,
you know, why is that? Because usually it's the wrong side making
the stipulations. If I'm buying into it, I want to have the
guarantees. Not the other way around. You know, you as the seller
would want to give me fewer guarantees, right? You want to have
as little responsibility to me as possible. But now here... Passionate realtor.
Maybe. No, that's such an oxymoron.
Right, והכא מוכר קא מתני. ve'hacha mochar ka matni.
But now it's like the quote-unquote wrong side making these stipulations, right?
And therefore משום דפטומי מילי בעלמא הוא. mishum de'pitumei milah be'alma hu.
That's what he's saying. He's saying is your reason because of that?
Right? That the, and so since the seller, who would normally not
do these things, is doing it, he obviously clearly doesn't mean it.
אלא דתניא, ella de'tanya, wait a minute, what about this? That's, you
know, that כשיש לו לקמא אותך keshu le'kama otach that whole thing,
כשיש לו לקמא אותך. keshu le'kama otach. אחזיר לך achzir lach that
that the second part, right? מתניתא, matnita, you know is the ברייתא,
braita, right? That's the how we said it. שיהיו לך מעות אחזיר
לי. she-yihyu lecha ma'ot achzir li. So the, you know, the buyer
says it to the seller,
מותר.
Why? דמוכר הוא דבעי אתנויי, de-mocheir hu de-ba'ei itnuye, but מוכר לא
אתני לוקח הוא דקא מתני.
mocheir lo itni lokayach
hu de-ka matni. Okay
and that, you know, we said why is it okay? Because usually
who would be making all these, usually, you know, most again, most
things would be seller, not the buyer. But here's so the buyer
is doing it so we said that's okay.
They just want their understanding it just base...
wait wait we're really in the middle of a thought. Let me
see if I can, you know, let me see if I can
explain it. No, no it's fine. So now לוקח
מתני,
lokayach
matni, so then therefore ומי מאי שנא רישא ומי מאי שנא סיפא?
u-mi-mai shana reisha u-mi-mai shana seifa? Now we're getting into all this.
And then on this ואמר רבה סיפא דאמר לדעתי, ve-amar Rabbah seifa
de-amar li-da'ati, right?
So basically לכשאירצה, le-khish-eirtza, so we said that's okay. So now okay
he's building all this up, right? He just so far he just
worked through what we said before. He said okay oh well this
is okay and this is not okay and why is this okay?
Because he's not locked in. He said לכשאירצה. le-khish-eirtza. He's just building
up. Now now here's his thrust. So okay fine. So now having
said all that explanation of this ברייתא, braita, we still have to
tie it back to this particular question on אמימר. Ameimar. But so
דאמר לדעתי, de-amar li-da'ati, he says oh לדעתי, de-da'ati, הא לא אמר
ליה לדעתי, ha lo amar lei li-da'ati,
if he did not say לדעתי, li-da'ati, לא אמרינן פטומי מילי דעלמא
הוא. lo amrinan pitumei milei d'alma hu. So basically the same thing.
He said so לדעתי li-da'ati means so he really means it, right?
You know, like it's okay because he really means he'll do it
and it, you know, so so what does that not mean? It
does not mean it means it doesn't mean since this is a
valid sale it does not mean פטומי מילתא, pitumei milta, right?
If it was פטומי מילתא pitumei milta that means he didn't mean
it. If he didn't mean it it wouldn't be a good sale.
So but he did mean it, that means it is a good
sale, right? So
so if he did not say לדעתי li-da'ati הא לא אמרינן פטומי
מילתא. ha lo amrinan pitumei milta. So so then basically in this
case in
it doesn't seem like he said in this case לדעתי. li-da'ati.
If you look at if the case of אמימר Ameimar he did
not say אי טרפו לך מיניי מגבינא לך שופרי שבחא ופירי. i
tarfu lach minei magbina lach shafrei shevacha u-peirei. You know so
so then why are you saying that it that it works? He
didn't say לדעתי, li-sha-da'ati, he didn't say he didn't say לכשאירצה. ke-she-eirtza.
He's locked himself into it. He locked himself into it.
If he didn't say מדעתי mi-da'ati then it's a binding stipulation because
he doesn't have the choice
to
exercise yes or no he can't be fickle about it. If it's
מדעתי mi-da'ati it could be what he's saying today tomorrow the wind
will blow a different direction.
So then you know so then why are you saying that it's
just פטומי pitumei you know why are we say over there פטום...
we're not saying פטומי מילתא over here right? So why?
So אמר ליה נעשה כמאן דאמר ליה לדעתי. amar lei na'aseh ke-man
de-amar lei li-da'ati. Alright fine.
So it's you know so really in your case you know so
basically אמימר Ameimar is saying in my in you know in my
case he's not locking himself in. He's you know he's an iffy
thing that
if you know if I want to I'll make good for you
on the this and that and the other. Since this was again
this was you know this was done after and this was done
after the sale, right? And the contract specified otherwise. So since all
and since this was done after the sale, contract specified otherwise and
he he didn't say I'm really going to do this. He's saying
I'll consider it. That's you know since he's saying that, right?
So it's not actually you know it's not נעשה כמאן, na'aseh ke-man,
he didn't actually say that, but the point the point is that
it's done after the sale. So if it's done after the sale
he's read it read it in as saying as if he said
I will consider doing it, right? Since he did it after the
sale clearly he didn't mean it, right? You know if it if
it were at the time of the sale, you know then then
that'd be something else. At the time of the sale and he
said לכשאירצה, ke-she-eirtza, right? Then
that then that'd be fine. You know like then be a good
sale. And then and then it would be up to his discretion
to you know decide whether or not to go make good
in the in the case that there'd be a loss on the
loan. But over here what he's saying is that you know that
this is done afterwards
and do we bind him to it? So you'd think that since
he didn't say לכשאירצה ke-she-eirtza he's bound to it. Why are we
not saying פטומי מילי דעלמא? pitumei milei d'alma? But the answer is
since this was done after the loan, as if he's saying לכשאירצה,
ke-she-eirtza, so really is פטומי דעלמא. pitumei d'alma. לכשאירצה ke-she-eirtza he can
just as easily say not אירצה. eirtza. So he's not bound to
it. So that's why the get it? Like this this is you
know this
is at the time of the
sale as the underlying
idea. The underlying idea seems to be with all these components that
you're clarifying is it the person is locked in either verbally or
at the correct time at the beginning of the transaction it's going
to be structured and considered like a loan and then you've got
a ribbis problem. If he's not locked in then for whatever reason
either because it wasn't explicit enough or it was at a different
moment in the transaction like afterwards then it's more like a sale
because somebody can exercise their choice and renege so to speak.
Well let's see if this assumption holds you know because we're going
to go have a number of cases on this.
Okay. Does that make sense what I said as going through?
So far.
So again the point is you know I'm trying to stress this
is not כמאן דאמר למיגזי k'man d'amar l'migzei right since he's doing
it later after the sale as if he's saying I will optionally
choose to do so that's option choose okay you know he's not
bound to it. He didn't say I optionally choose but like the
point is since he's doing it later as if he said that.
That's why he's saying פטומי מילי pitumei milei right? He says I
will make good but like you know which made us think that
okay you know. Anyway the whole point is he asks this whole
question פטומי מילי pitumei milei the idea of quoting that whole thing
was to get to the fact that he said פטומי מילי pitumei
milei and that is the same thing as here even though they're
different times. Right? In the first case he really did say כשארצה.
keshe'ertzeh. Here he didn't say כשארצה keshe'ertzeh but as if he did
because it was done later. Right? So are we okay are we
clear with that? Okay
fine.
Okay this is a very interesting case. Did anyone have a question?
Did I answer your question? Sort of maybe?
There was a little procession there in that little piece there that
okay.
ההוא שכיב מרע דכתב לה גיטא לדביתיה.
hahu shechiv mera dechativ
lah gitta l'dveiteh.
So
this guy on his deathbed he has a wife and
he gives her a get. Now why would someone give a get
if he's going to die anyway?
Anyone?
יבום. Yibum. No no don't look at the notes. Anyone remember? יבום
Yibum right? That's why they want to give a get right? Not
to get her out of יבום Yibum I mean to get her
out of you know what I mean so not to have her
obligated in יבום. Yibum. So אנגיד
ואתנח angid ve'itnach he was like you know sighing and you know
whatever however you translate this but he was expressing his displeasure at
having to do this.
He groaned okay one is groan and the other is sigh. So
אמרה ליה אמאי קא מתנחת? amrah leh amai ka mitnachat? So what
you know what's all this about? Why are you so sad? אי
קיימת אנא
דידך i kaymet ana didach if you stay alive I'll remain your
wife right? So like she's sort of
hopefully he's not Cohen.
So yeah so well so she's sort of undermining the entire idea
of this
get right? So אמר זעירי פטומי מילי
דאמרה.
amar Zeiri pitumei
milei d'amrah.
That's what he said it doesn't mean anything. Right? You know. ואמר
רב אמי v'amar Rav Ami but you'll see I
mean there's a
fundamental you know difference over here. אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא
amar leh Rav Acha
miDifti l'Ravina
ואי לאו פטומי מילי מאי? ve'i lav pitumei milei mai? So what
do you
mean what's פטומי מילי? pitumei milei? What about that? Let's say we
didn't even have this idea of פטומי מילי. pitumei milei. Would that
still be good? בידה קיימא למישדי תנאה בגיטא? biyada kayma l'mishdei tna'ah
b'gitta? בידו קיימא למישדי תנאה בגיטא? biyado kayma l'mishdei tna'ah b'gitta? What
do you think פטומי מילי pitumei milei just say the whole thing
doesn't make any sense. She's not the one that gives conditions in
the get he is. Right? He gives her the get. She doesn't
make conditions.
She doesn't have her condition here or she said she said don't
worry you know look I see you're hesitant to give me the
get don't worry I'll remarry you if if you know you get
better. Right? You know give me the get right? You're worried that
like I don't want to end this marriage you know what I
mean.
אי קיימת אנא דידך. i kaymet ana didach.
Yes if you if you stay alive you know you get better.
אי קיימת אנא. i kaymet ana.
It's very romantic. Yes it's romantic פטומי מילי pitumei milei just making
her feel good. I love you honey.
Right? But it's still a get it's still a divorce. That's that's
the point. פטומי מילי דאמרה. pitumei milei d'amrah. Like you know like
it doesn't mean anything. She doesn't have to remarry him right? So
she can marry someone else right? Whoever it is. Right? Even if
even if he gets better. So you know so that's that's the
import of that. So you said oh פטומי מילי דאמרה. pitumei milei
d'amrah. But but the point is what does פטומי מילי pitumei milei
have anything to do with it right? In other words this whole
thing can't get off the ground. She doesn't make תנאים בגיטין. tna'im
b'gittin. He does. The husband says okay you're divorced on this condition
she has no power. I mean that's unfortunately the way it is.
So like what's this פטומי מילי? pitumei milei? What it's not even
part of the
conversation right? Because she didn't have the power to reject the get.
Right? That's like so like that's the question in other
words why
do you
bring in פטומי מילי pitumei milei like you know this just makes
no sense. מהו דתימא m'ha d'teima no מהו דתימא. m'ha d'teima. So
why are we saying this? מהו דתימא m'ha d'teima הוא גופיה אדעתא
דידה קא גמר ויהיב גיטא. hu gufeh ada'ata d'didah ka gmar veyahiv
gitta. So then just say oh so she said that then... it
can be reversed, right? So then, yeah, then קא משמע לן ka
mashma lan that no, that it's not then he then it does
then her condition, you know, hasn't gotten off the ground and then
his דעת da'at to be סומך somekh on the condition is similarly
nothing. It's all פיתויי דעלמא pituyei d'alma and then it's a good
גט. get.
Here it's not even talking about verbal, now it's just his intention
essentially. Yeah, yeah.
And
well his intention versus on her verbalization, yeah.
Which is like another
step.
Yes, another step removed, right.
Where earlier we saw the verbalization, here it's just his intention.
Right. Good point.
He could have put in the—he
could have put in the
גט get that if I get better then this doesn't apply.
But then the question is, you know, would that even be a
good condition? Anyway, but the point is that, you know, that you
know,
that's why we're saying פיתויי דעלמא pituyei d'alma because you might have
thought like oh, actually this might have had some halakhic substance that
he then now gave her this גט get on that condition, in
which case then it would be, you know, but no קא משמע
לן ka mashma lan that like, you know, like we don't say
any of that. So all right, let's try to do as much
as we can. הלוהו על שדהו. hilvau al sadeh-u. So you know,
this is a whole case of
ביתוס בן זונין, Boethus ben Zunin, right? So this guy throws a
loan for a hundred
dollars—this is the value of the
loan—and he gives in and you know, and he has and he
pledges a, you know, let's make it easy, a
three-hundred-dollar משכון, mashkon
right? So that's so obviously it's worth a lot more. And then
what he says—and the משנה Mishnah says—that אם אתה נותן לי מכאן
ועד שלש שנים
הרי אלו שלי.
im attah noten li mikan
v'ad shalosh shanim harei elu sheli.
So
if you don't give it to me, if you don't repay,
then I get it, right? Then שלי. sheli.
No repay,
שלי, sheli, mine, right?
So what happens?
So you might think is that you know, that's like interest, so
to speak, right? In other words, you have to repay the loan.
If I don't—usually what the משכון mashkon is, they well they give
the משכון mashkon for security of the loan, but like, you know,
but you'd think, you know, unlike our bank, right, the bank sells
the house and excess of the value of the mortgage it has
to refund the borrower, right? So but here you don't have to,
right? You're getting a three-hundred-dollar
repayment for a hundred-dollar loan. Why isn't that ריבית? ribit?
Or three years from that. What? Three years, right? This is three
years.
Okay, whatever it is.
And it looks like ריבית ribit and but
it does look like ריבית, ribit, right? The long you know, the
תורה Torah law makes no difference how long a loan is. I
lend you a hundred dollars, whenever the loan becomes due, you have
to repay me, right? And just the hundred dollars though, right? So
but here you're paying him three hundred dollars essentially, right? So why
is that okay?
That seems to be great predatory lending.
Right. Why isn't—exactly. So why isn't that predatory lending? Right. So that's
the question we're going to discuss. אמר הונא בשעת מתן מעות קנה
הכל ואחר
מתן
מעות לא קנה אלא כנגד מעותיו.
amar huna b'sha'at mattan ma'ot kanah
ha-kol v'achar mattan ma'ot lo kanah ella k'neged ma'otav. So
he says he differentiates between when this was done, right? This whole
condition. If this was all done at the time of the drawing
up the contract, then he gets the whole field,
you know, the whole three hundred dollars, even though the loan's only
a hundred dollars. So why? Then then you know, like then that's
the idea is again, is this an—this is you know, just to
fill in the blanks, this is like again, like a little bit
more of like an is like kind of like an אסמכתא asmakhta
in some ways, right? Do we
say he's קונה? koneh? So so you know, so the idea here
is and this is what I wanted to—I want to read this
in the תוספות tosafot. if we can. I'd like to read this
in the
תוספות. Tosefot I never remember where
where it is.
I did it all yesterday, but I can't find where it is
right now. But okay anyway, but the point is,
you know, that this is at the time of the—you differentiate between
where when the אסמכתא asmachta, was done, basically. Like if it's at
that if like we said before, it was done afterwards, you know,
like that whole case of I'll make good with you, if someone
liens it—takes it away from you, I'll give you the פירות, peirot,
I'll give you the שבח, shevakh, I'll give you the everything, right?
If that's done afterwards then it's just merely בפיטויי דעלמא. b'pituyei d'alma.
So if it's done at the time, then that's you know, like
a part of the contract or the sale. So what he's essentially—so
that's what he's basically saying. בשעת מתן מעות קנה הכל. b'sha'at mattan
ma'ot kanah ha-kol. If it's done later, then לא קנה אלא כנגד
מעותיו. lo kanah ella k'neged ma'otav. Okay, then he only gets his,
you know, hundred dollars and the two hundred dollars, you know, gets
goes back to the you know, the guy who borrowed the money.
I'm not dealing with the problematic aspect of the case, we're just
dealing with the verbal. If it's a
verbal contract,
that's what it seems like, where
we're ignoring that other aspect.
Yeah.
Right.
So,
he only only gets you know the amount of the money to
be good on the actual value of the loan he went through,
but רב נחמן אמר Rav Nachman amar אפילו אחר מתן מעות afilu
achar matan ma'ot קנה הכל. kanah hakol. He says no, even if
it was done later, even if it's done later, he gets it
all. So, yeah, so רב נחמן עובדא Rav Nachman uvda גבי ריש
גלותא gabei Reish Galuta כשמעתיה. kishmatiya. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman was
consistent
and you know
this case happened and he ruled by his own ruling. So קרע
יהודה לשטרא. Karah Yehuda l'shtarah. So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda ripped this
whole thing up. He's like, you can't do that, right? That's no
way, that's not going to work. So, אמר ליה ריש גלותא amar
lei Reish Galuta רב יהודה קרע לשטרך. Rav Yehuda kara l'shtarach. So
ריש גלותא Reish Galuta says,
"Hey listen, you know, like רב יהודה Rav Yehuda tore up your
שטר." shtar. אמר ליה Amar lei דרדקא קרייה? Dardaka karaye? Did a,
they call them דרדקי dardakei or like
teachers, so דרדקא dardaka are the children. So, did did like some
little kid tear it up? No, גברא רבה קרייה. Gavra rabbah karaye.
You know, like look, he tore it up, there must be a
reason, right? I may have to reevaluate my opinion over here. So
חזא בה טעמא וקרייה, chaza bah ta'ama v'karaye, he must have, you
know, like I should have read that, he must have seen a
reason to do this. So איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, okay that's one
version. So איכא דאמרי ika d'amri אמר ליה amar lei דרדקא קרייה.
dardaka karaye. He said no, not as a question, "Did a child
tear it up?" A child must have torn it up, he has
no idea what he's doing right, because you know רב נחמן Rav
Nachman is generally actually the כלל klal is הלכה כרב נחמן בדיני.
halacha k'Rav Nachman b'dinei. Like רב נחמן Rav Nachman we פסקן pasken
like רב נחמן Rav Nachman almost all the time.
So and not by רב יהודה? Rav Yehuda? Yeah. So דכולי עלמא
לגבי דידי בדיני דרדקי נינהו. D'kulei alma l'gabei didi b'dinei dardakei ninhu.
Everyone compared to me, everyone's like a child, you know, like they
don't know what they're doing, I do. So, so obviously, you know,
according to version one, we need to like reassess this this whole
thing here, right? According to version two, no, you know, like he
didn't know what he was doing. So הדר רב נחמן, hadar Rav
Nachman, interestingly, אפילו בשעת מתן מעות לא קנה ולא כלום. afilu b'sha'at
matan ma'ot lo kanah v'lo klum. And he says you know טאקע,
takeh, okay now certainly according to the first version where he said
that you know this גברא רבה gavra rabbah tore it up, I
gotta reevaluate. He did reevaluate, right? That's a הדר, hadar, he changed
his mind, like you know what no, it's no
good, right?
So
basically the idea is like, so here's the question: if it's at
the time, here's like I guess the way to think about it
is, if something was made at the time of the sale and
it's a verbal commitment, right, and you know, do you say that
if it's discussed verbally at the time of the sale in the
negotiations that that becomes a condition of the sale because it's being
discussed, and then you know because there's literally it linearly, right, there's
discussion, there's sale, there's discussions and then the sale concludes. So if
a conclusion of the sale predicated upon all the things that were
discussed before, in which case it could be אסמכתא קניא asmachta kanyah
right? Or do you say that no, just words, you know everyone
negotiates, and then you know the sale was for whatever it is,
right? The loan is for whatever it is. You know like,
so how much is this verbal declaration you know become part of
the sale? If it's done afterwards, certainly it isn't, right, part if
it's done after the sale then this whole verbal stuff is פטומי
מילי. pitumei mili. But if it's done at the time of the
sale, that's like that's the line we're trying to straddle. You know
when does this become a binding condition and when is it just
like okay you know like, yeah I don't really think three years
down the line, in other words three years down the line I'm
going to come up with the money three years down the line,
it's not going to come to that, so he agrees to it
right but he didn't really mean to agree to it, he just
wanted to get the money.
So then there's no ריבית ribbit problem just like a sale.
Well if you say that it's okay, meaning if it's a condition
of the sale, oh no, because if the reason why it might
not be a problem is because why
why would it not be why would it, let me see if
I can get this straight, why would we say that this is
not a problem because then you're saying because we're saying this is
a, oh because in condition of a sale then it would be
ריבית. ribbit. So let me think about this for a minute.
Yeah no, in our case no, yeah so that's what רב נחמן
Rav Nachman is saying, that בשעת מתן מעות לא קנה ולא כלום
b'sha'at matan ma'ot lo kanah v'lo klum because it is an אסמכתא,
asmachta so he never thought it would happen. If he never thought
it would happen, he didn't mean to do it. If he didn't
mean to do it, then you can't then call him to task
on this later. He didn't mean
it. So
are we dealing with
a,
it's לא קניא lo kanyah
meaning, I think there are two I think there are two I
think there are two issues. One is like you know is this
even like you know a sale and then is it a ריבית
ribbit problem? Right let's even see if this gets off the ground.
These issues here, it's not like earlier where we. It’s not structured
as a sale and there’s no ריבית ribbis problem, or it’s not
structured as a sale and there’s a ריבית ribbis problem. It’s now,
I’ve lost exactly what
the...
so you know, again, I think what we’re trying to, you know,
right now I think it seems like we’re more on like the
אסמכתא asmachta, issue. You know, like, can we even say this is
like, you know, this was done in good faith? Right? On both
sides. That the borrower really meant to say that, you know, because
again usually what happens is... and you know, and again, the issue
to think in the back and that’s where I want to get
to תוספות Tosefot at some point and I don't know if we’re
going to, is when a משכון, the idea of the משכון is
that it’s repayment for the loan. So when is something you know,
done as a משכון and when is it done as you know,
he’s just really saying this he didn’t mean to hypothecate it for
his loan, right? And and usually you do you know, usually the
idea of a משכון is it's worth at least as much as
the value of the loan if not more because otherwise why would
I accept something as collateral if the loan is worth less than
the loan? Right? So, you know, and I don’t think I’m going
to ruin the surprise a little bit, you know, it might be
different if you pledge land versus pledging מטלטלין. You know, there was
there's a general assumption that people were very reluctant to part with
their land because like, you know, it’s their land! I mean, most
people were farmers back then anyway, right? Like you know, this is
their livelihood. It’s not like you know, as opposed to you know,
whatever, my car, right? You know, so so that’s why it might
be less even less serious in the case of land. You know,
now if it’s you know, if the idea of land is that
it’s more your ancestral land, let’s say I bought this land you
know in a business transaction and then I did that, then maybe
that’d be different, right? Because it’s not my ancestral land. It’s you
know, some thing I bought from you, so you know, I may
be more serious with it. Whereas like you know, an אסמכתא, asmachta.
whereas in land, if I pledge land to you to make good
for the loan, you know, I never really think it’s going to
come to that. I I don’t want to be landless! I’m just
saying that because I want I want this hundred dollars I really
need it, you know? The land’s worth three hundred dollars, I never
I never really think that you’re going to you know... three years
down the line I never think this is going to happen. So,
so anyway, רב נחמן Rav Nachman was saying even if בשעת מתן
מעות besha'at matan ma'ot you know, doesn't work because he just said
it to get the loan. He never thought that like it would
come to that three years down the line.
And look, the idea is אסמכתא. asmachta If you if you see
over here: איזהו אסמכתא דאמר להו אם לא נתתי לך מכאן ועד
שלוש שנים הרי היא שלי הרי היא שלו. Eizehu asmachta de-amar lehu
im lo natati lecha mikan ve-ad shalosh shanim harei hi sheli harei
hi shelo. So what do you mean? Like you know, רב נחמן
Rav Nachman said it’s not good, right? רב נחמן Rav Nachman just
said even a time בשעת מתן מעות besha'at matan ma'ot it’s not
good, right? But what about our משנה? Mishnah Our משנה Mishnah says
it is good, right? Our משנה Mishnah, said that, right? But as
תוספות points out, it was something מניומי Minyumi used to do. He
he did exactly this. Our משנה Mishnah, says it's okay.
Because it's a כתב ketav maybe we don't know how it was
done in our משנה, Mishnah. it was בשטר beshetar or basically בשטר...
beshtar... Oh that's interesting.
But assuming that it you know, we're assuming that the conditions are
the same. So, אמר ליה אני אמר אסמכתא קניא ומיניומי
אמר אסמכתא לא קניא. amar lei ani amar asmachta kanya uminyumi amar
asmachta lo kanya.
Listen, I used to say... let's let's get the timeline right. I
used to say just like our משנה, Mishnah? right? That אסמכתא asmachta
is קניא. kanya. I was I was okay with this משנה. Mishnah.
You know, I was convinced to change my opinion by whom? ומיניומי
אמר אסמכתא לא קניא. uminyumi amar asmachta lo kanya. Okay, so you
ask him! מניומי Minyumi is the one that convinced me otherwise. So
you’re asking me the משנה? Mishnah You know, I I just held
by מניומי. Minyumi. Ask מניומי Minyumi why he disagrees with this משנה.
Mishnah That’s what that’s what he means. ומיניומי קשיא ממשנה... uminyumi kashya
mi-mishna... so fine, okay, how do you answer our משנה Mishnah? מניומי,
Minyumi, right? Our משנה says it's okay, you’re saying it’s not okay.
We we... are we all good here? Okay. איבעית אימא, iba'it eima,
מתניתין רבי יוסי דאמר אסמכתא קניא. matnitin Rabbi Yose de-amar asmachta kanya.
Okay, how do you answer our משנה? It’s somebody else's opinion, right?
It’s not a universally accepted opinion, it’s רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose opinion,
and I don’t hold like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. All right, that’s
easy enough. איבעית אימא אמר ליה קני מעכשיו. iba'it eima amar lei
k'mini achshav.
Okay, now that’s that’s different, right? In other words, did he say
at the end of three years, right? So is this a... did
he say at the end of three years then I get it,
right?
Or did he say it’s mine from now in the event that
you don’t pay from three years... in three years. So if he
does קני מעכשיו, k'mini achshav, that changes it. That’s not considered an
אסמכתא asmachta because he’s getting it right away. He gets it right
away, then you know, then the guy’s not thinking you know like...
it’s different like you know thinking okay, something may happen three years
from now and then everything will happen three years from now, the
field will be his three years from now and I’m not going
to pay this loan three years from now and then... so you
know, then he’s like saying okay, I’m just going to agree to
it. But if he’s like really getting it now, you know, like
you know, like it just makes it more real, you know what
I mean? So for him to agree to that, even though
the the time for the loan payment is three years from now,
but if he’s agreed to this that the guy gets it now,
just like makes it real, you know, like... again, this is a
fine line over here as you can see.
It becomes more of a פסק psak because here he’s adding more
detail therefore it’s considered more... Let me just see something. So, you
know,
now now remember, like there are two there are a
couple issues here. Okay fine, like... So we have to say that
presumably as I said before like you know this whole פירות peirot
are or place in escrow right? You know if it's let's say
a one year loan you can keep it there or for three
years and you know I guess someone has to has to go
sell the fruit put the money you know in in a bank
account and then whichever way it falls out you know is as
is what is whichever you know if it's if it was your
אסמכתא asmachta then you get then you know you the purchaser get
it but if it's but if I paid right you know then
these fruits are really mine because it was never yours it was
only yours if I didn't pay and then these are mine and
I get the value of the fruit. So you know but so
that's that's what we have to say.
So you could really mess it make this complicated what if the
second of these three years was a שמיטה shmita year?
Oh boy.
Okay anyway so the fact that he to get to the point
though מעכשיו me'achshav you know it it takes
effect now so
takes effect now like the so it is you know so that's
like a part of the sale. אמר ליה אמריוקא amar leh amaryuka
so what's interesting is I love these guys names we'll just do
a little bit more because I want to get to a better
stopping point just another two minutes. אמר ליה אמריוקא אמר קשישא בני
דרב חסדא דרב אשי amar leh amaryuka amar kashisha benei de rav
chisda de rav ashi so you know
אמר קשישא amar kashisha the
thing thinking of מעכשיו me'achshav versus later maybe this is a this
is a אחר זמן achar zman maybe there's a point that also
so these guys yeah whether this is actually their names or you
know two sons basically had the same name so one was you
know so how do you know who's whom so one was called
the older one was called the younger one so it's like mr
baby and like mr adult you know like really that's like I
wanted to translate it literally ינוקא yanuka is a kid and קשישא
kashisha is old
many times often children were given numbers rather than names oh that's
interesting.
So any so anyway this is not the first time I remember
this from another גמרא this is not the first time they quoted
these נהרדעי neharde'ei הכי אמרי נהרדעי משמיה דרב נחמן אסמכתא בזמניה קניא
ולא בזמניה לא קניא hachi amri neharde'ei mishmeih de rav nachman asmachta
bizmanei kanya v'lo bizmanei lo kanya so
so רב נחמן rav nachman who says that even בשעת מעשה מכר
besha'at ma'aseh mecher is not is not קונה koneh so he says
that if it's at its time then it then it does you
know at the what what we say what do you mean at
this time at the time we didn't say we'll explain it at
the time it works at the time it doesn't work so אמר
ליה כמידי בזמניה קניא ולא בזמניה קניא amar leh k'midei bizmanei kanya
v'lo bizmanei kanya what do you mean at the time or everything's
at the time or not I don't understand so I don't translate
this exactly so it means דלמא הכי קאמר ליה אשכחיה בגו זימניה
ואמר ליה קני dilma hachi ka'amar leh ashki b'go zimnei ve'amar leh
k'ni so now
it doesn't even have to be at the time of the sale
if remember there are a couple of times here there's there's you
know there's the time of the initiation of this contract then there's
the you know that's time one then there's time two which is
when it's due then there's time three okay it's not due now
what do you do right like you know like you have to
repay it so anytime you know this is
due
right so anytime between you know in this space between when it
is loaned
and
when it is due is considered like the זמן zman to repay
right is up until this point to repay so that's that's what
he means so he says
that אשכחיה בגו זימניה ואמר ליה קני ashki b'go zimnei ve'amar leh
k'ni within the
time right
then then he does the I'm sorry
the אסמכתא asmachta would work in that period is that what we're
talking
about yes yeah he said when you know if it's at its
that's what he said he said that according the נהרדעי neharde'ei version
of this that אסמכתא בזמניה קניא asmachta bizmanei kanya the אסמכתא does
work if it's at all doesn't have to be at the time
that
the loan now we're extending it until
the time it becomes due so you know he says that at
the if it's within that time then קניא kanya the lender does
does you know he doesn't get he's קונה koneh he's קונה koneh
this field
so what's the idea of this the idea of this is where
is it קניא kanya look at רש"י rashi דגמר ואקני דאי לא
אמר ליה למה אמר ליה הלא עיניך עכשיו בטובה de'gemar v'akni d'ee
lo amar leh lema amar leh halo einecha achshav b'tovah like he
has to be serious and we're going to end with this like
you
know why because this is the borrower let's say saying to the
lender at the time
you know what if it doesn't become you know if I don't
end up paying you can have this field
right so why would he say that right clearly he you know
clearly you know he doesn't need to so the fact that he's
volunteering this information or offering means he's serious therefore it's קונה koneh
ואחר זימניה ואמר ליה קני v'achar zimnei ve'amar leh k'ni but he
made it afterwards and he said okay you know what I I
missed out this is a $300 field just take it right then
then he doesn't לא קניא lo kanya מאי טעמא mai ta'ama כיסופא
הוא דקאמר ליה kissufa hu d'ka'amar leh
he's like he feels really embarrassed like you know he's going to
see this guy on the street until a loan is due he
doesn't have to pay him back after the loan is due he
has to pay the guy back he's like oh my god I
can't believe it I haven't paid him back I got to make
good you know so so he did but he didn't really want
to give him the $300 field for a $100 loan. ולא היא
*ve-lo hi*. Gemara says no, דאפילו בגו זימני נמי לא קני *de-afillu
be-go zimney nami lo kani*. והאי דקאמר ליה קני קסבר כי מטי
זימני לא ליתי ליטרדן *ve-hai de-ka-amar lei kani kasavar ki mati zimney
lo leite litar-dan*. Basically, you know, we go back to what we
said originally. Rav Nachman says that אסמכתא *asmachta* is never קונה *koneh*,
right? It just isn't. So why would he say it at the
time? He's like, oh, you know, I don't want to have to
worry about it.
I don't want him to come bother me, because you know, let's
say I don't pay. Then he's gonna see him every day. He's
gonna say, well, נו *nu*, where's the money? Where's the money? Where's
the money? You know? This way he's like, oh, okay, until this
day he's not gonna bother me. Afterwards I'm gonna see him every
day, let me just say, all right, you can have it. But
he didn't really mean it. It's just an אסמכתא *asmachta*. He said,
you can have it because I just don't want him coming to
me and bothering me. But so basically what we see from over
here at least at this point is that according to Rav Nachman
who reverses the opinion, אסמכתא *asmachta* is just not קונה *koneh*. All
right, that's
to be continued as to you know whether we hold by this,
whether we continue with this.
All right, go ahead, I had a question.